<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The wicked plots, and perfidious practises of the Spaniards, against the 17. provinces of the Netherlands, before they tooke up arms. Being gathered out of severall Dutch writers, by a lover of truth, and an unfained hater of oppression and tyrannie, the bane of commonwealths: [text defaced]</title>
            <author>Scott, Thomas, 1580?-1626.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92749</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E123_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212764</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871340</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871340</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156151</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92749)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156151)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 22:E123[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The wicked plots, and perfidious practises of the Spaniards, against the 17. provinces of the Netherlands, before they tooke up arms. Being gathered out of severall Dutch writers, by a lover of truth, and an unfained hater of oppression and tyrannie, the bane of commonwealths: [text defaced]</title>
                  <author>Scott, Thomas, 1580?-1626.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A lover of truth = Thomas Scott.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "19 Octob: 1642".</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: third sentence of caption title defaced; unable to supply, as anr. cop. also defaced.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:156151:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The wicked Plots, and perfidious Practiſes of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> againſt the <hi>17.</hi> Provinces of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> before they tooke up Arms.</head>
            <head type="sub">Being gathered out of ſeverall Dutch Writers, by a lover of truth, and an unfained hater of Oppreſſion and Tyrannie, the bane of Commonwealths:</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall ſpeak ſo much touching the cruel, inhumane, treacherous, perfidious; yea, unnaturall practiſes of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> in theſe parts, and elſewhere, which may ſufficiently delineate him in his deſerved colours, that whoſoever beholds him may mourn to ſee this <hi>Hazael</hi> ſo to tyrannize over the innocent, &amp; that the Lord ſhould permit, and the earth beare ſuch an unheard of monſter: yet notwithſtanding much more might be added in ſundry other particulars, as the Dutch Chronicles mention, and other Writers have wel ſet out: amongſt which, although I my ſelfe be a ſtranger by Nation to them; yet ſince the time of my aboad here, having attained ſome underſtanding in the Language, I have thought fit to ſpeake ſo much, which in my reading I have obſerved.</p>
            <p>Firſt, thou art to underſtand, gentle Reader; that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> was loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly received here in the 17. Provinces, and a ſolemn oath was taken on both parts; the King for his part ſwore to maintain all their Lawes &amp; Priviledges, and they to him all due homage &amp; allegeance: He preſently demanded of them a ſumme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, whereupon the States did aſſemble, and collected for him 40. millions of Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines, of <hi>Brabants</hi> money, to be paid in 9. years, and they paid it into the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, and although it was more then they had paid before to his predeceſſors, yet upon this he tooke great diſpleaſure againſt them, and, as they write, he for this did hate them to death.</p>
            <p>But he pretended this to be the cauſe of his wrath, becauſe he ſaw that there were ſome among them, that did defie the Pope and all his Religion: but that could not be, for the City of <hi>Aelſt</hi> was as ſuperſtitious in that Religion as <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe; for they did perſecute the Reformed Religion even unto death: and yet for all that both they, and 170. fair Villages that belonged unto them, were by them plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſpoiled of all their goods, and many of them wounded and tormented for to confeſſe where their money was, and many were killed. Thus much by the way.</p>
            <p>My ſcope and chiefe intent, is to ſhew the firſt and juſt cauſe of the wars in the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> whereby the diligent Reader (not partially affected) may clearely underſtand, that the <hi>Netherlands</hi> did not rebelliouſly take up Arms againſt a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Prince, (as ſome ignorantly thinke and ſpeake) but juſtly and religiouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves againſt a perfidious Tyrant who ſought their ruine, by all poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meanes he could, and the ſubverſion of the whole State. A long while they pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently underwent his cruell oppreſſions, and intolerable vexations, as the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries clearely manifeſt; till there was no hope, but either they muſt become ſlaves in ſoule and body, worſe then that of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> they and theirs for ever, or elſe be butchered by mercileſſe executioners of a cruel Tyrant. This Tyrant having a purpoſe to innovate all things, to root out ancient inhabitants, and to fruſtrate all
<pb facs="tcp:156151:2"/>the Laws, Cuſtomes and Priviledges which himſelfe had ſworn to maintain; knew not how better to effect his evil ends, then by raiſing a bloody Inquiſition to ſet over them for their government;<note place="margin">The Inquiſition was there fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e yearesefore.</note> which ſaid Inquiſition (raiſed in <hi>Spain</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded and pronounced certain Articles, the tenth of February 1568: which were confirmed by the King, the 26. following. Now becauſe it may appeare I do them no wrong in this charge; I will lay down the Articles themſelves verbatim.</p>
            <p>The moſt ſacred Office of inquiſition, ſo often attempted in the Netherlands by his Majeſty, and hindered untill this time, ſhall be inſtituted and advanced in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>with</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hole adminiſtration of the Nethe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>That the Emperour with his two ſiſters, having given over all affaires, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Netherlands, ſhall retire into Spaine unto Vs, being aſſured that they ſhall never returne more to doe any harme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Theſe being diſpatcht, we muſt alſo draw the King to us, and keep him for ever that he part not, and not ſuffer any Flemings to have acceſſe or conference with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>That the King write unto, and command the Clergie of the Netherlands, that with the Inquiſition they ſhould accept of</hi> 15 <hi>new Biſhops, the which ſhould be free from all ſecular juriſdiction, yea in caſes of treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>The ſubjects of the Netherlands through their malice &amp; waywardneſſe, will revolt and move ſeditious and tumults, pleaſing to all but our companie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>The Princes and Noblemen, heads and authours of thoſe factions, with the ſubjects, muſt be taken away, and the others reduced unto reaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 <hi>They ſhall hire at our charge theeues and ſpoilers of Churches and Images, whoſe offences ſhall be by all the world imputed to Rebels, by ſome ſubtill meanes, and ſo we ſhall vanquiſh them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 <hi>That all Comerce, Negotiation, Liberties, and Priviledges, ſhal be rooted out, &amp; that all be reduced to extream povertie, wherby the realm ſhal be permanent for Vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>No man of all thoſe Countries (except he be of our faction) ſhall be held wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to live; and finally all to be rooted out: and all Goods, Poſſeſſions, Arts, and Trades, and all Orders to be taken away, untill there may be a new Realme, and a new people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 <hi>In this action the wiſe and valiant Duke</hi> Alva <hi>ſhall be imployed in perſon; whereas any other, were he of the blood Royall, or a Prince, ſhall be of no eſteeme: ſo as being ſuſpect yea in the ſmalleſt matters, they muſt be diſpatcht.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11 <hi>No Contracts, Rights, Promiſes, Donations, Oathes, Privileges, and ſolemne Aſſertions of the Netherlands, ſhall bee of any force for the inhabitants, as being guiltie of high treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>But above all we muſt have an eſpecial care that in theſe matters of ſo great weight and moment, we proceed not violently, but by meanes, by degrees, and that diſcreetly, to the end the Princes, Nobilitie, and inferiour ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ects may mutinie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, ſo that one may perſecute, yea execute the other untill at laſt the hang man be executed himſelf. For in all Chriſtendom is there not a Nation more fooliſh and indiſcreet, and whoſe levitie and inconſtancie may ſooner be deceived then theſe Netherlanders, and God puniſheth them accordingly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were other Articles found in preſident <hi>Vergaes</hi> chamber at <hi>Antwerpe</hi> and there printed; and thoſe are more cruell then theſe, but not more ſubtile.</p>
            <p>By theſe Articles &amp; unlimited power of theſe lawleſſe inquiſitors, no man had any aſſurance of life or goods for a day, but were indanger continually to be called in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:156151:2"/>queſtion, either for the Law of their God, or for ſome work of mercy, which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther religion, morall equity, or the bond of nature called for: or elſe if they had colour for none of theſe, they would impoſe ſuch unreaſonable taxations, which if the Cormorants had not their gorges crambed full, they would make prey of all, whether by right or vvrong it mattered not. But my purpoſe being to avoid prolix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie, and to paſſe by impertinences and needeleſſe repetitions, I will come to that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> intended.</p>
            <p>In the yeare 1565. a match was concluded for the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> and the nuptials were ſolemnized at <hi>Bruxels,</hi> whither all the Nobility and Gentry of the countrey were invited, and accordingly there met of them about 400. who like faithfull <hi>Moſes</hi> being grieved to ſee the daily oppreſſion of their brethren by the hard task-maſters of the Inquiſition, who not onely robbed them of their goods, but alſo by inhumane cruelty, and unnaturall butchery, deprived them of their lives, who daily led them as ſheep unto the ſlaughter: The conſideration hereof they joyntly layd to heart, and hereupon (being met upon this occaſion) they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to preſent a petition to the Princeſſe of <hi>Parma,</hi> which they did the 5. of Aprill next following. The E. of Breedrod delivering the Petition,<note place="margin">The ſubſtance of this relation is not unſutable to theſe times.</note> humbly requeſted a favourable anſwer. Three dayes after they received this anſwer, <hi>viz.</hi> they ſhould ſend two of their Nolbemen to the King, by whom ſhe would write in their behalfe. The Lord of Barlamont being preſent, after their departure ſaid <hi>(like a flattering Courtier)</hi> they were a company of Raſcalls and Beggars.</p>
            <p>It was concluded that the Marqueſſe of Bargen, and the Lord of Mountigny ſhould go into Spain, who humbly preſented their ſuit to the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng, but could get no anſwer in 16. moneths after.</p>
            <p>The 26. of Auguſt <hi>Anno</hi> 1566. the Princeſſe of <hi>Parma</hi> ſent for the Gentrie, telling them ſhe had received Letters from the King, containing promiſe that all ſhould be well, and that the inquiſition ſhould ceaſe. And for the Proclamations they ſhould not be of force, but his Majeſty would take ſuch order as they and the States ſhould well like of. The Princeſſe alſo gave them tolleration for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, on condition they ſhould not deface, nor breake downe the ornaments of the Churches: for, there had beene before this time vile and leude perſons that frequented the meetings of the Reformed; theſe went into the Papiſts Churches, ſtole their ſilver and what was worth carrying away, and brake downe their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: but the reformed ſuſpected that this was done by the appointment of the Princes, neither was their ſuſpition without good ground, for it is to be ſeene in the Kings let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>Art.</hi> 7. that ſhe had order to hire this raſcall company to doe this vilany,<note place="margin">Emanuell de Miter ſaith, that in Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders they tooke <hi>50.</hi> of them at one time, and hanged <hi>22.</hi> and whipped the reſt.</note> which fact was imputed to the Proteſtants, to the end that they might not onely be odions there, but alſo ſeeme guilty, even in the judgement of other Nations, howbeit the offenders were puniſhed with impriſonment, yea, with death, even by the reformed themſelves, who joyntly confeſſed the action unlawfull, and were ſo far from giving occaſion of offence in this nature; that Papiſt burgers themſelves offered good ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, that no ſuch thing ſhould be attempted by them. Who then can make any doubt that they were free from having any hand in thoſe outrages laid to them? the very oppoſites in Religion being judges, who as appeares were willing to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake for them; now as their faithfulneſſe brought ſo good effect for their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſo did the Lord worke that the truth of religion found many friends likewiſe, the Lord wonderouſly proſpering the courſe of reformation, in ſo much that in ſhort ſpace they had in <hi>Flanders</hi> 60. Aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mblies, ſome Churches they themſelves builded, but were by Duke <hi>d Alva</hi> ſoone caſt downe, who erected Gallowſes of them, and hanged them upon them,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:156151:3"/>
            <p>The Princeſſe of <hi>Parma</hi> alſo began to entertain ſoldiers with pretence to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Church-robbers, but intended indeed to take away the ancient liberties and priviledges of the <hi>Netherlanders,</hi> wherefore ſending certain Companies to <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencyn,</hi> the inhabitants denyed them entertainment, who for that vvere proclaimed Rebels the 14. of December, ſoone after they were beſieged, ſacked, and many of them put to death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it for Religion, but his aim was to get their lands &amp; goods.</note>But before they of <hi>Valencyn</hi> denyed entertainment to the ſouldiers, the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had received letters out of <hi>Spain,</hi> from the Marqueſſe of <hi>Bargen,</hi> ſhewing, that the King vvas exceedingly incenſed againſt the <hi>Netherlanders,</hi> that he had in he preſence of many vovved to be fully revenged of them, though it vvere vvith the hazard of all his Countries; that hee vvould make them an example to all the World, and vvould invite the Pope and Emperour to aſſiſt him in this quarrel. Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the receit of the Letters the Nobility aſſembled at <hi>Dortmond</hi> to conſult vvhat vvere beſt to be done, but concluded not any thing, ſome judgeing it ſafeſt to joyn, and make head to reſiſt his tyrannicall fury, others ſeeking rather to eſcape by flight.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">As the Grau of Egmond, and the Grau of Horn, and many of the Gentry at Bruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, <hi>1568.</hi>
               </note>The cruelty of this Inquiſition did notwithſtanding increaſe, and many ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers came into the Countrey, that ſome of the Countrey forſook their houſes, and reſorted towards Freezeland, and ſome did ſtay at home, and went to meete Duke <hi>Alva,</hi> and welcommed him into the Countrey, and ſhewed him all the kindneſſe that they could, but he very ſhortly tooke off moſt of their heads, ſo that he did ſo terrifie the inhabitants, that there fled out of the countries more then 100000. houſeholders, beſides many that were taken in flying, were taken and hanged, and all theſe had their goods confiſcated to the King.</p>
            <p>Now the D. of <hi>Alva</hi> did command all the inhabitants to pay the hundreth peny of all their goods, and of all that was bought and ſold, the which ſome of the States did yeeld unto: And then he commanded them to pay the twentieth peny: and then he commanded the tenth peny of all things that were bought and ſold,<note place="margin">The like taxations, though in another manner, have been practiced here before the Parl.</note> ſo often as they ſhould be ſold. Some of the States did make their humble Petition to the Duke, and to the Princes, ſhewing them that it would drive all trading out of the land. The Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> told them that he would have it, though it did ruinate all the land: but if he ſaw them to doe their beſt to pay it, he would deale favourably with them. But he ſaid that it was againſt the Kings honour if they ſhould not pay it, ſeeing it was his pleaſure to require it. And now did the Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion impriſon and execute many of the richer ſort, as well Papiſts as of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church: and if they were rich there was no eſcaping for them. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever was found to have any hand in way of ſuit and petition to have the tenth peny to be remitted,<note place="margin">Al the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were filled, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as they were forced to prepare more, and filled them alſo.</note> they were adjudged to have committed high treaſon againſt God and the King; and all theſe muſt forfeit life and goods to the King, and not any of their children to enjoy one peny worth of the ſame: but (poore Orphanes) they muſt beg their bread. And ſomewhat had been buryed certain months, they cauſed to be digged up, and hanged on the gallows, and ſome to be burned, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had not the ſacrament, and confeſſed before their death; but it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would confiſcate their goods to the King: yea when theſe inſatiable gold-thirſty and bloud-thirſty wretches wanted colour to cover their injuſtice and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, they had their officious imps (falſe witneſſes) ſuborned by <hi>Jeſabel,</hi> to get <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard; vvitneſſe <hi>Martin Hutton,</hi> vvho vvas one of the Inquiſitors Clarks, and (being committed to priſon) did acknovvledge that he had made many falſe teſtimonies againſt ſundry rich perſons, ſome vvere of the reformed Church. Here might fitly be brought in the hundred Merchants of <hi>Granado,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:156151:3"/>vvho vvere of the Romane Religion, and vvere never other; vvhat pretence had he to cauſe them to be murthered all in one night, and then preſently to command all their goods to be brought to his treaſurie or Exchequer, whoſe eſtate was vvorth more then 28. hundred thouſand pound ſterling? Novv as this tyrant vvas a devourer and deſtroyer of the lives of men, ſo he did preſume to uſurpe further not onely upon civil ordinances, but upon the things of God; ſo that thoſe that vvere married in the reformed Church, he forced to be married againe: and if they vvere rich, he tooke them from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir husbands, and gave them to his ſouldiers to make prize of them: thoſe that were babtized in the reformed Church, be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to be baptized again, contrary to Gods word, and to the decree of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent councels, ſo intolerable were the burthens that this cruel <hi>Pharaoh</hi> laid, ſo exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive was his cruelty, that he filled all places with blood, <hi>bloud touching bloud,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks. For in ſmall townes he executed 50. and in great townes 200. and 300. or 400. And in places as men travelled from one towne to another, they might ſee many that his Souldiers had hung up in trees to death, and ſome were worth 80. thouſand guldens, and ſome leſſe: yea this tyrant did confiſcate ſo much lands and goods, as by his accompt ſent into Spain, did amount yearely to 8. tun of money ſterling, beſides the many thouſands that he and his ſouldiers had. All the money that he did exact out of this land in 6. yeares, did amount to more then 50. millions of gold. And if any were knowne to have any thing that did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to any that were put to death, and had not brought it to the knowledge of the Inquiſition, they did looſe both life and goods: yea the 16 of February 1566.<note place="margin">The like cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties may juſtly be feared to be among us, if the Parl. ſhould be ſubdued.</note> he gave ſentence in his court at <hi>Madrill,</hi> that they were all traytors againſt God and himſelfe. At <hi>Vtrecht</hi> he beheaded a widovv that vvas 84. yeares old, becauſe ſhe had before lodged a preacher one night, vvhoſe living vvas vvorth foure thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand guldens yearly. And at <hi>Maſtricht</hi> a father for lodging his ſon that he had not ſeen in a long time, that vvas fled for religion, vvas put to death. And at that place there vvas one put to death for giving a vvidovv a peck of corn for an alms, vvhoſe husband this bloody court had put to death. And many vvomen vvere put to death, becauſe they received their husbands in the night that vvere fled for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; yea they have killed vvomen great vvith child, and ripped up their bellies, and taken out the child and killed it, and ſome they have fleyed alive, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red drums heads vvith their skins, and ſome they have tyed to a poſt, and made a ſmall fire round about them, and ſo roaſted them to death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The like cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty they did at Oudwater.</note>At <hi>Naerden</hi> they received the Spaniards friendly into the tovvne, vvho promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them both their lives and goods; and as ſoone as they came in, they comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them to come to the Statehouſe vvithout their Armes, the vvhich they did, and the Spaniards gave fire upon them and murthered them all: and then they ran about in the tovvn and raviſhed the vvomen,<note place="margin">Take heed of ſuch treachery here.</note> and after Killed them and fired the tovvne. The yong children that lay in the Cradle, they quartered them, and tooke them upon their pikes, and ſo vvent up and dovvn the tovvne rejoycing in their cruelty.</p>
            <p>Such ſavage cruelty is ſcarcely to be found in any hiſtory, vvhat Chriſtian heart can hear it, and not be affected vvith deep ſorrovv? yet behold ſome monſters here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in have been found, that have beene ſo far from humanity herein, (for he that hath humanity in him vvill commiſerate others calamities) that they have applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it, as if he had in all theſe outrages done God good ſervice. Amongſt the reſt, I ſhall content my ſelfe at this preſent, but to name the holy Father the Pope, and one of his chiefe ſonnes in this buſineſſe. The Pope ſends his Legate to commend theſe ſo rare exploits, and cals this cruell Duke <hi>Alva</hi> his beloved ſonne, ſends
<pb facs="tcp:156151:4"/>him a coſtly ſword, the hilts whereof were of gold, and a hat wrought with gold, and beſet with rich and coſtly ſtones, thanking him for his good ſervice in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Romiſh Religion and ſubverting of heretickes. Howbeit that his chiefe ſon I mentioned (exceeding this man of ſin, in the ſin of cruelty, as if he would ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie himſelfe to be ten fold more the child of Satan, then his father the Pope) thinkes not ſo well of it, his name is <hi>Vergas,</hi> the Preſident of this bloudy Inquiſition; for going ſhortly a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter into <hi>Spain,</hi> he told the King, that he &amp; Duke <hi>d Alva,</hi> did marre all in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> by ſhewing ſo much mercy to thoſe people.</p>
            <p>Concerning this Duke <hi>d Alva,</hi> of whoſe outrage and cruelty ſo many haue felt, and perfidious dealing which many haue found by lamentable experience, whereby may eaſily appeare of what ſtamp his exceſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e mercies are, even ſuch as the Wiſe man ſpeaks of,<note place="margin">Theſe words he ſpake at a ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet as he ſate at the table, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing bee had done the King ſo good ſervice.</note> 
               <hi>Pro:</hi> 12.10, <hi>the tender mercies of the wicked are cruel.</hi> In which he prides himſelfe, boaſting he had ſlaughtered eighteen thouſand and ſix hundred, in form of juſtice, in ſix yeares time, and ten tunes ſo many he and his Souldiers murthered otherwaies. And many more would he doubtleſſe have murthered, had not the Lord reſtrayned and limited him, for his deſire herein was as hell, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſatisfied: Witneſſe the purpoſe of his proceeding againſt the Magiſtrates of <hi>Bruxels,</hi> becauſe they did not collect the tenth peny ſo as he defired. He tware that he would have it, and before he would let it fall or remit it, the Sun and Moone ſhould leaue their ſhining, ſo he vvent to Bruſſels, and commanded the executioner to prepare ladders and ropes to hang up that night in their doores 70 of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, and gave them his vvarrant in vvriting vvhat they ſhould be: But God in his providence prevented this his cruel purpoſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1573. <hi>April.</hi> 1.</note> in that there came news that the Graue of Mark had taken in the Brill; ſo the tyrant did not goe forvvard vvith his bloody enterpriſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">I have inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced but <hi>4.</hi> or <hi>5.</hi> towns, but there were ſcarce any town eſcaped their cruel pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laging, except they had bribed their Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders with excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding large gifts.</note>Thus having given you a t ſte of ſome of thoſe many things I have o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſerved concerning the intolerable oppreſſion, &amp; vvorſe then ſalvage cruelty of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, exerciſed upon the people, vvhich they endured and laboured under the ſpace of ſixteene years; I will novv leave theſe cruel tyrants to the Lord for judgement, and addreſs my ſelf to ſpeak ſomevvhat further concerning this Earle of Mark, vvho had thoſe Gentlemen vvith him that fled. Before this hee had layne vvith his ſhipping in England, but the King of Spaine ſending his Ambaſſadour to our Queen (vvho vvas then in peace vvith him) to deſire her that ſhe vvould not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his ſubjects to have their harbour in her land, and that ſhe would not give them or ſuffer them to have any reliefe whereby they ſhould make head againſt him: and hereupon the Queene ſent and commanded them out of her harbour, and ſhe commanded that they ſhould not be ſuffered to have any proviſion in her coaſts, ſo that now they had no other means but onely God, who did in his mercie provide for them better then they expected. For they were purpoſed to have gone for the Taſſel, and to have taken ſome towne about that part; but when they came neere that part, they had the wind contrary that they could not come there, ſo they went for the Maiſe, and came with their ſhips before the Brill, and there they went preſently &amp; took it; yet the Duke of Alva had his forces in the towne, neere ſo m ny as they were, whom they preſently killed and chaſed out of the towne, and out of the Iland. The Prince of Orange being in France, and hearing what had happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he ſent them ſouldiers with as much ſpeed as could be out of France. And within one moneth after Duke Alva ſent certain companies to Vliſhing to keep that place ſtrong for himſelf, and many of the commanders were come into the towne: So the Magiſtrates commanded the citizens to come preſently upon the Statehouſe, ſo they told them they muſt lodge Spaniards in their houſes; and they knowing
<pb facs="tcp:156151:4"/>how they hade uſed the citizens in all places where they came, they told the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates they would not have the Spaniards in their towne, the Magiſtrates asked them which of them it was that did refuſe to receive them. They ſaid, All of them. So the Magiſtrates ſeeing them ſo earneſt againſt the Spaniards, they joyntly tooke their Armes, and killed and took priſoners all them that were in the town, and with their Ordnance they ſhot at his ſhips where the Spaniards were, and they made away. And of thoſe that were taken, there were the names of about 80 that they had in writing from Duke Alva that dwelt in the Iland, that they ſhould put to death. So thoſe of the Bril ſent their Souldiers with ſpeed to help them.<note place="margin">He had appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thoſe to bee executed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were the chiefe that ſtood againſt the pryment of the tenth peny.</note> And ſhortly the Prince of Orange came with forces and defended them; and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther townes ſeeing the crueltie of the Spaniards, forſooke the Spaniard, and joyned with them, and took the Prince of Orange to be their Protector, yet the States not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding did remain in obedience to the King ſome ſeven yeares after.</p>
            <p>Again it is further worthy to be noted that theſe Provinces did three times ſend to the King their Noblemen, but could obtain no mercy, and many more times they went to the Princeſſe of <hi>Parma,</hi> and made their humble petition for redreſſe of their oppreſſion, but could not obtain any favour, then they made friends to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Queen of England, and to the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> and to the Emperour, who did earneſtly entreat by their Ambaſſadours for them. The King of <hi>Spain</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered their Embaſſadours with theſe words; he bade them tell their Maſters, <hi>That they ſhould meddle with their own ſubjects, and not with his, for he knew wel enough how to rule his ſubjects without their Counſel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anno 1575.</note> Now vvhen our Queens Majeſty found his unreaſonableneſſe and cruelty, then and not before, ſhe aſſiſted them with Armes.</p>
            <p>His ovven ſon Prince <hi>Charles</hi> did intreat for them, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t it vvould pleaſe him to let them have their Lavves and Priviledges, and that they might not be ſo oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and vvithall he told his father that thoſe Countries did belong to him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marplam</hi> in his Cronicle. <hi>Anno 1567.</hi> Pray the like may not be he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in <hi>England.</hi>
               </note> and that they vvere given him at his Baptiſme, for the vvhich his father ſent him to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and he never came out again. If the Lord vvould not have forgot vvhat <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alek</hi> did, long after, for ſmiting the vveakeſt and hindmoſt of his people, hovv may vve in equity forget the infinite murthers, and ſpoiles, this cruel Tyrant hath exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted vvhereever he hath prevailed? And vvho can forget in ſpecial that bloudie attempt againſt our ſelves, in the year 1588.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould trace this Tyrant from place to place, I ſhould runne in infinitum, having made the name of Chriſtianity hateful, by his cruelty, amongſt the Heathens that knovv not God further then the light of nature: for it is confeſſed by the <hi>Spany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> themſelves, that ſome of the chief of the <hi>Indians,</hi> vvho were to be burnt to death,<note place="margin">They were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted by a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh prieſt to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> minde, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life there was one place for joy, &amp; another for tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> being told of heaven and hel, they asked whither the <hi>Spaniards</hi> vvent vvhen they dyed? It vvas anſvvered to heaven, <hi>Oh then ſayd they we will never come where the Spaniards are.</hi> But not to run ſo far, I vvill reſt content to keep me vvithin the bounds I chiefly intended concerning theſe Countri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s. When the Citizens of <hi>Leyden</hi> vvere in great extremity, by reaſon of a long ſiege, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> proffering conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of peace, if ſo be they vvould yeeld up the Citie and themſelves to them, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned anſvver; <hi>Not while they had a right hand to hold the ſword, or a left to eat,</hi> but if they ſhould be driven to fall into their hands, they would rather burn the Citie and drovvn themſelues, then to ſubmit to them, of vvhoſe perfidiouſneſſe they had had ſo lamentable experience: and vvhen ſome of the Citizens preſſed a yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, in reſpect of the extremity of famine, a Burgermaſter, called <hi>Peter Adrianſon,</hi> ſaid; <hi>Loving friends I confeſſe the famine is great, and that ſome doe die for want of food: yet rather let us agree to eat up on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> another, as it ſhall fall by lot, begin with me firſt, and divide me amongſt you.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:156151:5"/>
            <p>At <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> by the appointment of their Governour did come into the Citie in battel order, and marched up and down their ſtreets, and ſhot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their houſes, and made a tumultuous noiſe, as if they had been ſo many devils, for one day and two nights, and took the keyes from the Magiſtrats, and ſet watch at the Ports;<note place="margin">No ſort excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> whereby they put the Citizens in ſo great fear, that many women with childe fell in travel, and ſome dyed with feare: and they went by 12 or 20, into the beſt houſes, &amp; commanded them to prepare them the beſt cheer, as boyled and roſt, &amp; other dainty diſhes, as they liſt to call for; and beſides beer, they would have at leaſt two ſorts of wine.<note place="margin">They did offer them two parts in money, and the <hi>3.</hi> in cloth, but they cryed all for money.</note> And all the chiefeſt Citizens houſes had at leaſt ten of theſe gueſts. And they all cryed out for money, and ſaid that they would have 15. moneths pay before they went out of the City, of them; and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates told them that they would procure them in cloth, and apparel, and money the ſumme; but they all cryed out for mony, and that mony they would have before they went away; ſo at the laſt, the Magiſtrats got the mony, which did amount to 400. thouſand Guldens. And the charge they were at, which theſe companions did coſt the Citizens,<note place="margin">There ſtands in the Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle a quire of paper of their cruelty againſt this City.</note> was 600. pound ſterling the day, and thus they were oppreſſed with them 28. dayes, in which time they had made them all rich ſutes, ſome of ſat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin and velvet, and ſome of cloth of gold: and one of them had a cuſhion of velvet, vvith theſe vvords in letters of gold, <hi>I am the Dutchmans Bride-well Maſter.</hi> And thus they got rid of them for the preſent. And about tvvo yeers after they came again, and then they uſed the Citizens much more cruelly, for theſe divels did bring ſtravv, and ſet on fire, &amp; put it into the houſes, vvherby they ſet nine rich ſtreets on fire, and burnt them vvith many rich and coſtly goods, and rifled the Citizens of all their rich and coſtly jevvels, and ſilver-vvorks, vvith their money, and three dayes did they torment the inhabitants for money: and in this time there vvas murdered of the citizens above four thouſand. The money they took at that time is reckned for more then 40. tun of gold, beſide the Ievvels and the loſſe they had by fire, vvas as much as the reſt. And thus vvas the beſt city of Marchants in Europe ruinated.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In the yeare <hi>1580.</hi> the States proclaimed K. <hi>Philip</hi> to have loſt his right, by reaſon he vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated his oath.</note>Divers things being manifeſted of the Spaniards cruelty, I vvill adde one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of their trechery, and that of a famous perſon to his neereſt familiars; yea vvhen he pretended ſvveeteſt familiarity and friendſhip, Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 6. a Spaniard by birth, invited divers Nobles and Cardinals to a banket, vvith a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to poyſon them all, The meeteſt inſtrument he made choyce of to effect this, vvas a Spaniard, one <hi>Caeſar Burgia,</hi> his ſvvorn ſervant. The Pope ſhevved himſelf vvonderfull pleaſant to avoyd ſuſpition, and drank a carouſe to them all; vvilling that his truſty ſervant to fill from ſuch a bottell he knew well: which he did ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry effectually to the Pope himſelf as well as to the reſt.<note place="margin">A Spaniards kindneſſe to his friends.</note> After the company was departed, the Pope perceiving by an alteration in himſelf, what was done, and that he muſt die now alſo, ſayed to <hi>Burgia, This is a right Spaniſh trick.</hi> It is written of them that they are ſo expert in theſe exploits, that if <hi>Judas</hi> himſelf were alive, he might goe to them to Schoole.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
